Lucas Fernandez Nicolau

iOS Engineer

Portfolio » in LinkedIn » Portfolio » in LinkedIn »

M Medium » GitHub » 🙏 Released apps »

About me

I am an iOS engineer passionate about the combination between quality software, a beautiful UI, and a great UX.

My programming journey started when I was 14 years old (2012), exploring the wonderful world of possibilities that were opened when my first "Hello, world!" was coded.

In 2019 I was one of the students worldwide who won Apple's WWDC19 Scholarship Badge \square , being invited to attend the event in person.

Professional Experience

iOS EngineerJun 2022 – presentNate ☑London, England

Being part of Nate's iOS team, the world's only universal shopping app.

Main responsibilities:

- Refactor some MVC code to MVVM;
- Tons of UI components using view code;
- Add features with its own tests (unit and snapshot tests);
- · Code Reviews;
- Deal with ever changing environment of a startup;
- Work abroad in a 100% English environment;
- Discuss new features and implementations with the UI/UX and PM.

Tech details:

- MVVM-C;
- Swift Package Manager;
- RESTful APIs integration;
- · Protocols;
- Dependency Injection;
- · View Code;
- Unit Tests;
- · Snapshot Tests;
- Git/Github.

Jun 2021 - Apr 2022 Remote Globant ♂

Working directly with Google as a client, developing (alone) an iOS app for them utilizing iOS network-related APIs, using Objective-C.

Main responsibilities:

- Use low level/not very known iOS APIs, like NetworkExtension;
- Decide how to implement new features and how to structure new code added into the project;
- Discuss and decide UI/UX changes;
- Create a lot of UI components using view code;
- Maintain a large iOS app for a big company alone;
- Manage CocoaPods (Firebase) in the project;
- Define required test steps for QAs;
- Deal with constant requirement changes and still be able to deliver new features on time.

Tech details:

- Objective-C;
- VIPER;
- NetworkExtension;
- Firebase:
- RESTful APIs integration;
- · Protocols:
- Dependency Injection;
- · Object-Oriented Programming;
- · View Code:
- · Git/Github.

iOS Developer

São Paulo, Brazil BTG Pactual 17

Worked as one of the developers in the iOS development team of BTG+, the digital consumer bank from BTG Pactual, the biggest investment bank in Latin America.

Main responsibilities:

- Perform code reviews consistently;
- Develop extremely reliable features;
- Implement complex UI components (i.e.: different chart types);
- Participate in refinement meetings with the rest of the squad (Backend/Android developers, UX designers, QA's and product owner);
- Release and manage test and production versions in TestFlight;
- Deliver features following strict deadlines.

Tech details:

- Swift:
- MVVM-C;
- Dependency Injection;
- View Code;
- · Protocols;
- Jenkins;
- TestFlight;
- CocoaPods (the project itself was structured in pods);
- Git/GitHub.

Feb 2021 - May 2021

iOS Developer Jan 2019 – Dec 2020

Apple Developer Academy ☑

My routine was based on solving real-world problems while developing my abilities in programming, design, business, and soft skills.

During this time I was able to build and release more than ten apps while exploring almost every Apple framework and technologies (UIKit, WatchKit, SpriteKit, SceneKit, CoreML, CreateML, SwiftUI, ARKit, CoreData, CloudKit, etc).

Main responsibilities:

- To be present in every aspect of the app development lifecycle (problem finding, research, UI/UX design, programming, business plan, app release, and management);
- Opportunity to lead some teams during the whole process of the app development;
- Follow SCRUM methodology;
- Deliver complete apps quickly and effective (from 2 weeks up to 2 months);
- · Care about accessibility and inclusion;
- Manage projects from scratch using GitHub.

Tech Details:

- Swift;
- UI/UX;
- Research:
- · Interface Builder;
- XIBs:
- · View Code;
- Figma;
- Git/GitHub;
- UIKit;
- SpriteKit;
- CoreML;
- SwiftUI;
- Multipeer Connectivity;
- MVC;
- MVVM.

Jan 2016 - Dec 2018

When I finished high school, I decided to enter mobile app development (because I already had some experience with programming, since I started to code at 14 years old, in 2012).

I think about this period more as a personal learning experience than a professional experience, but I am including it here for the following reasons:

- I focused on the good practices of the development process, using Git/GitHub and following design patterns;
- I released many apps on the Play and App Store, including:
 - An iOS app called StudyO, that was featured on the App Store and became the #2 app in the productivity category;
 - An extra-official app for my University, that became the number one choice for the students, reaching more than 16k downloads.
- I practiced the UI/UX ideation process;
- I also developed a software solution for an Industrial Automation company, integrating it with a cloud database (Firebase). This app is used daily by the company since 2018.

Education

Computer Science

Feb 2017 - Dec 2020

Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie 🗷

Brazil

High School

Jan 2013 - Dec 2015

Colégio Objetivo Granja Viana

Brazil

Projects

Portfolio 2

My website displaying my main apps and solutions.

SIGLA 2

IoT + iOS solution to manage chemotherapies procedures in hospitals in real-time.

Your study hub

App created to help students to manage their classes subjects, documents, reminders, and calendar. Created entirely by me: UI/UX, development, App Store releasing/management).

CaptureML 🗷

CaptureML is a game that uses Machine Learning at its core.

Made with CoreML and using a camera overlay, showing what's seen by the device's camera all the time, making the app's view "transparent".

The Hatch: Splashing Around

Game created using Apple's SpriteKit and Multipeer Connectivity frameworks.

Troco Certo (Correct Change) □

App created to help illiterate people to achieve independence when shopping.

This app has the minimum amount of text possible, utilizes a lot of symbols, visual representations, audio, and well-known features (like using voice to speak the value of the purchase). It can also be used by blind people since we developed it thinking in accessibility and inclusion all the time.

Awards

Apple's WWDC Scholarship Award 🗷

2019

Apple

Skills

Swift iOS Development

Objective-C MVVM-C

MVC Unit Tests

SwiftUI Git/GitHub

Xcode Apple's Human Interface Guidelines (HIG)

UI Design C/C++

JavaScript React Native

Flutter Python

Figma Android Development

Kotlin Java

Languages

Portuguese English

Native speaker Highly proficient

Publications

[PT-BR] Usando Codables em Swift 5 para consumir uma API de filmes 🛭

Medium

[PT-BR] Criando sections personalizadas dinamicamente 🗵

Medium

	_				
L	o	u	rs	es	

0041000	
Practical Design Patterns in Swift LinkedIn Learning	2020
Swift 5: Protocol-Oriented Programming LinkedIn Learning	2020
iOS Development: Architecture LinkedIn Learning	2020
iOS: Unit Tests and TDD Alura	2020
Git e Github: Branches strategies, conflicts and Pull Requests Alura	2020
Git e Github: Control and share your code Alura	2020
Become an iOS 11 App Developer LinkedIn Learning	2018
Swift 4 Essential Training LinkedIn Learning	2018
Xcode 9 Essential Training LinkedIn Learning	2018
iOS 11 Development Essential Training: Application Architecture LinkedIn Learning	2018
iOS 11 Development Essential Training: Design a User Interface LinkedIn Learning	2018
iOS 11 Development Essential Training: Intermediate UI Design LinkedIn Learning	2018
Fundaments and Practices in Cloud Services using Swift, IoT and Cognitive Computing Instituto Eldorado	2017
Concepts and Fundaments in Programming Logic, 00P, JavaScript and RESTful APIs Instituto Eldorado	2017

Android - Advanced 2017

TreinaWeb

React Native 2017

TreinaWeb

Hobbies

I love to watch movies and enjoy their soundtracks! I'm also passionate about football/soccer and the awesome social impact caused by the game, giving me a lot of great memories in my life. I have fun developing "silly" apps to help me when doing boring stuff. Binge-watching TV shows is a huge quality of mine too. And, above all things, my favorite hobby will always be spending time with my family.

References

Pedro Henrique Cacique Braga, Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie | Apple Developer Academy https://linkedin.com/in/phcacique

Joaquim Pessôa Filho, Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie | Apple Developer Academy https://www.linkedin.com/in/joaquimpfilho

Antônio Luiz Basile, Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie | Apple Developer Academy https://www.linkedin.com/in/antonio-luiz-basile-59773b24/